Okay, welcome back to Nagarjuna.
[laughs] [unclear].
And we're going to go to chapter 17,
which is, I don't know,
this chapter is weird
because you can understand it.
So I was thinking Nagarjuna's
sitting there and he's like
let me write one chapter
that they can understand.
And so, I don't know, you're
probably going to get bored now.
But here, let's go to it.
Now, it's worthwhile to say
that you might ask yourself
why did he write a chapter
that we can understand now?
You know, after sixteen
un-understandable chapters,
why does he suddenly
give us an easy chapter?
I think trying to guess
why Nagarjuna does stuff
is like a very interesting way
to spend a couple of hours.
All right, so here's
the name of the chapter.
LAS BRTAGS PA ZHES BYA BA
And I don't know if you
noticed, Tim, for example,
but he changed the spelling of BRTAGS PA.
Somebody changed the spelling,
probably Choney Lama.
And instead of saying an
investigation of karma,
he says let's investigate karma.
It's interesting, he made a verb.
Let's investigate karma.
So this chapter is called
"The Investigation of Karma".
All right, here we go,
let's go to the first verse.
Do you want to read, Tim?
,BDAG NYID LEGS PAR SDOM PA DANG,
,GZHAN LA PHAN 'DOGS BYAMS SEMS GANG,
,DE CHOS DE NI 'DI GZHAN DU,
,'BRAS BU DAG GI SA BON YIN,
- Good, okay. BDAG NYID?
- [Tim] Self.
- Yeah, but it's touchy
because he said BDAG NYID, me myself.
Where is he going to go?
When Nagarjuna says me myself, you're like
where are you going next?
Then he says SDOM PA -
- [Woman] Vow.
- Vow, but the verb?
Control yourself.
The verb for SDOM PA
means to control yourself.
So LEGS PA, LEGS SO LEGS SO.
'Well', to control yourself 'carefully',
to control yourself carefully.
And really it's BYAMS PA.
- [Woman] Love.
- Love, it's love.
BYAMS SEMS means thoughts of love.
PHAN 'DOGS GZHAN means to help others.
Thoughts of love where
you want to help others.
Now, all throughout these verses we go
BDAG NYID LEGS PAR SDOM PA DANG.
By the way when you go to the monastery
and hear the kids memorizing,
BDAG NYID LEGS PAR SDOM PA DANG
GZHAN LA PHAN 'DOGS BYAMS SEMS GANG
DE CHOS DE NI
No, Nagarjuna says don't say that,
say DE... CHOS, don't read it DE CHOS.
What's the difference?
DE... CHOS
That's CHOS, that's Dharma.
It's powerful, he says DE... CHOS.
What's DE?
SDOM PA and BYAMS PA
Control yourself from hurting others,
be nice to others, and love others.
DE, don't say DE CHOS, say DE... CHOS.
That's Dharma.
Yeah, and Choney Lama
adds a DKAR PO there.
DKAR PO, you have a DKAR PO shoes on.
- [Student] White.
- Yeah, white.
That's pure Dharma.
Choney Lama says, "That's
dharma as white as snow!"
Picture?
[all laughing]
That's Dharma DKAR PO.
Choney Lama says, "Nagarjuna said
"that's Dharma, that's what Dharma is,
loving other people and not hurting them."
But Choney Lama says, "And
that's as white as snow."
All right, GZHAN LA PHAN DE CHOS.
Now, what happens if you
do that kind of thing?
You get 'BRAS BU.
[student responding indistinctly]
You get results, and then.
Okay, here's $100.
Еhe Tibetan translator
put, okay Christina,
he put in the dual.
When he wrote fruits or results,
he used the ending which
means the two results.
Why?
It's at the end of the
third line if you can guess.
[students responding indistinctly]
TSE 'DI, TSE 'DI TSE GZHAN
Life, life.
Life, TSE 'DI LA -- in this life
and in your future lives.
For $100, how did the Yoga Sutra say that?
[student responding indistinctly]
In the first chapter of the Yoga Sutra,
they say that exact same thing.
@
Experienced in this life
and in the next life,
seen in this life and
seen in the next life.
All right.
Anyway, the results of
controlling yourself
from hurting others and from
thoughts of love towards others
is the SA BON of 'BRAS BU,
the two 'BRAS BUs,
in this life and your next life,
in the future lives, okay, got it?
There's nothing difficult
about that verse.
I don't know, Nagarjuna's losing it.
It's just a simple truth.
Then you're like suspicious,
you're like, well, where's he going now?
Here we go, next verse.
,DRANG SRONG MCHOG GIS LAS RNAMS NI,
,SEMS PA DANG NI BSAM PAR GSUNGS,
,LAS DE BDAG GI BYE BRAG NI,
,RNAMS PA DU MAR YONGS SU BSGRAGS,
DRANG SRONG CHEN PO means the great sage,
DRANG SRONG is sidhi,
okay, the great yogi.
Who's the great, the ultimate yogi?
- [Woman] Buddha.
- The Buddha.
Because sometimes he's called DRANG
SRONG CHEN PO -- the ultimate yogi.
You could got to use that in YSI somehow.
The ultimate yogi means the Buddha.
He said you can divide all karma,
LAS, into SEMS PA and BSAM PA.
[student responding indistinctly]
BSAM, past tense.
LAS LAS 'JIG RTEN SNA TSOGS SKYES
DE NI SEMS PA DANG DES BYAS
Opening-
[student responding indistinctly]
Yeah, thoughts and what they motivate.
So thoughts and thought.
Thinking and thought,
thinking and thunked.
Thinking and thunked.
That's a new verb, Pachi.
SEMS PA DANG NI BSAM PAR GSUNGS.
SEMS PA means intention,
and BSAM PA means what you intended to do,
which means what you say and what you do.
So he's covered how many?
He's actually covered
three kinds of karma.
SEMS PA -- mental karma,
and then BSAM PA,
what you say and what you do.
And that's all the kinds
of karma there are.
So the DRANG SRONG MCHOG,
the great, the ultimate yogi,
he said -- GSUNGS, "You
could divide all karma into
intending to do something and then
the things you intended to do.
Intention and intended.
LAS DE BDAG GI BYE BRAG NI
Now, if you want to divide those up,
SPYI BYE BRAG, right, here it is.
If you want to divide
up those kinds of karma,
DU MAR -- there's billions.
Just forget it.
YONGS SU BSGRAGS means
you can find described
hundreds, and hundreds,
and hundreds of divisions.
Basically those two:
intention and what you
intended to say or do.
Okay, got it?
Let's do some Sanskrit.
And I thought it would be nice to know
the words for intention
and what you intended to do or say.
So here we go.
Intention, or what you're thinking to do,
is called cetanā (chetana).
Chetana, say chetana.
[students repeat]
Yeah, the Tibetan is SEMS PA
which is the definition
of karma in Tibetan.
@SEMS PA
Karma is thinking to do something.
Raw karma, raw karma is intention.
It comes from the root
√cit which means to think,
which literally means to shine.
And in ancient times it was believed
that thinking illuminated the world.
If you ever died, the world would go dark.
See what I mean?
That's why the world is called "loka",
which means lucid, same root.
%Roach, also roach.
To shine from within so the
world is illuminated by the mind
so the mind is called √cit
which means √cit which means...
here it's called √kweit.
It used to be "kshit"
then it goes to @
then it comes "kshwit"
then is becomes "kweit",
and then it becomes white.
Or wheat because that becomes
white when you grind it.
So wheat means the white grain.
So the mind illuminates the world,
and that's why the mind
is called the whitener.
[laughs] Okay, got it? √cit.
And if you know Russian, I mean
there are many, many roots.
Schitat (считать) means to consider,
chitat (читать) means to read,
schitayu (считаю) --
I consider, like that.
Okay, or I read, okay.
Now, the opposite, cetayitvā (chetayitva)
is BSAM PA in Tibetan.
What you thought, which means
what you're doing and what you're saying.
The thunked, say.
And that's just a simple
passive form, right,
with the "ya", chetayitva.
That which you are thinking.
The "tva"
came into English as -tion,
like locomotion or action.
Makes it a noun.
Cool, we finished our...
just remember "chit" means to think,
and it's tied up with illumination,
"shchit" means shine.
Shine came from that.
All right, here we go.
Next verse.
So what's unusual about
this chapter so far?
Two verses in a row we understood
what the heck he's talking about.
And he doesn't seem to
have brought up emptiness.
And I assert that this is the first verse
he ever didn't bring it up,
and he's got two in a row,
which is really suspicious.
I mean this is where university scholars
say somebody added this chapter [laughs].
Which I don't think is true,
but anyway it's a little suspicious.
Okay, here we go,
,DE LA LAS GANG SEMS PA ZHES,
,GSUNGS PA DE NI YID KYIR 'DOD,
Universally miscarved.
,BSAMS PA ZHES NI GANG GSUNGS PA,
,DE NI LUS DANG NGAG GIR YIN,
You guys can figure this out.
What is SEMS PA?
It's YID KYI LAS, YID KYI LAS.
Karma of-
the mind.
What is BSAMS PA?
What's the thing you saw?
It's LUS and what?
- [Woman] Body and speech.
- Yeah, body and speech,
what you say and what you do.
Three in a row.
Something's definitely
going on. I don't know.
What's the picture?
Oh, even the picture was boring,
so I picked a picture from above.
Wait, yeah I'm sorry, no.
That's from the last one,
that's thinking and thought.
The balloon is thought,
I'm explaining it to you.
And here's talking and doing
which comes from thinking.
All right, let's go try to find
a verse which is challenging.
Oh, here's one [laughs].
In the next two verses he outlines
seven types of karma.
He promised us BYE BRAG,
right, what was that?
SPYI BYE BRAG
He promised us,
he promised us many categories of karma.
Well, here they are.
Here's the easiest one,
and it's intriguing
what Nagarjuna thinks
is a division of karma
because if somebody asked me
what's the different kinds of karma
I would say the 10 good deeds
or the 10 bad deeds, right?
And he goes off on this weird
thing which is so Nagarjuna.
Here we go.
Well, NGAG.
That's easy. Talking.
NGAG -- talking, all right?
Like NGAG DBANG is a typical Tibetan name
which means Vagishvara,
the power of speech.
So NGAG.
Then he says BSKYOD PA,
and you guys know MI
BSKYOD PA -- Akshobhya.
- [Woman] Unshakable.
- Yeah, unmoving like a mountain.
So what's kshobhya?
[student responding indistinctly]
Which means?
[students responding indistinctly]
Speech and action.
Physical action.
It's interesting, he calls it moving.
Moving your body.
So how many kinds of karma so far? Two.
Okay, two.
Okay, Tim, 200 bucks. From the Abhidharma,
RNAM RIG and RNAM RIG BYED MA YIN PA
Two divisions of... think of
weird things in Stanley's text
that have to do with karma.
[student responding indistinctly]
%Darn, $200! Dang!
Yeah, one is, what's the classic example?
When you take a vow.
When you get down on your knee
and you do this chicken posture thing,
anyone can guess your motivation,
it's MA KHYAB, right?
You could be thinking
about lunch, but [laughs].
So from the form, someone
can guess your motivation.
Later, according to the
Abhidharma, you have a?
[student responding indistinctly]
Like an aura or a halo around you
which is your vow's influence stays,
and it's invisible.
You can go to the bar and you can...
my translator in Mongolia, it's so cute,
said, "Geshe-la you ruined my life!"
The second time I went
there he had a beard
and I said what's going on?
He said, "Geshe-la we were on
national TV teaching dharma."
And I said well yeah, and he says,
"I can't go to the bar anymore."
[laughter]
Everybody's asking. I had to grow a beard
so they wouldn't recognize me.
So anyway, why are we talking about that?
You can't guess from the
bearded guy in the bar
that he had the karmic aura
of having taught dharma on national TV.
NGAG DANG BSKYOD DANG
Okay, those two are RNAM RIG.
What's the MA YIN DGAG, Tim?
If the first two are RNAM RIG...
[student responding indistinctly]
Yeah, then the next one's going to be
RNAM RIG MA YIN, a non-communicating aura.
Now he's going to talk about the aura.
So far we got two, we got
speech and physical movement,
Now we got RNAM RIG MIN.
And then he calls it MI SPONG BA.
You don't give up, you don't give up.
And Choney Lama says that's
Nagarjuna's short hand
for you don't give up MI DGE BA.
[student responding indistinctly]
Yeah, so it implies you are?
If you are MI DGE BA SPONG, you are?
If you give up MI DGE BA, you are?
DGE BA, yeah.
So why Nagarjuna calls good
deeds not-giving-up deeds?
It's because you don't give up bad deeds.
He defines, he's describing good deeds
as not-giving-up deeds, but that means
not giving up bad deeds,
which is good deeds.
[student responding indistinctly]
I'm sorry, giving up bad deeds.
Yeah, okay.
MI SPONG RNAM RIG MIN
I'm sorry, I screwed that
up, let's do it again.
MI SPONG BA means, yeah, I'm sorry,
Yeah, you don't give up bad deeds.
I said it right the first time.
Which is?
- [Woman] MI DGE BA
- A bad deed.
[student responding indistinctly]
No, not giving up bad deeds,
not giving up bad deeds
is a bad deed, that's all.
Okay, got it?
So I was right the first time.
So the category number three
is not giving up bad
deeds, which is bad deeds.
But we already covered the non-halo,
so this must be the halo, which
means the afterglow you get.
And Choney Lama says
from... and by the way
this is in the Abhidharma.
When you joined a trade in ancient India
you had to take a pledge
to follow that occupation.
And two famous pledges were
butcher and army, and military.
I will shoot people, I will kill people.
That's called a @.
What's that?
Anti-vow, it's an anti-vow.
I promise to follow my father's
trade for the rest of my life.
My friend in Argentina, her husband is,
kills the animals in the factory.
He's always depressed,
they don't know why.
[laughs] Okay.
So anyway, so how many we got now?
We got good, we got verbal karma,
action karma which you can see,
and then we got bad karma, halo,
which is having made a promise to.
And now we got SPONG BA'I
where you do give up bad deeds.
Okay, the halo you get when
you do give up bad deeds,
And the example of that
halo is the one you get
after you take your, when
you're just about to take your
medicine buddha initiation?
You take your Bodhisattva vows.
So that halo everybody in this class,
if you took the Nagarjuna's
Bodhisattva vows ceremony,
you have a halo around you forever.
Well, yeah. Well, some people
say it stops when you die,
but not for Bodhisattva vows.
So two kinds of halos.
Bad-good halo, talking, doing
that people can interpret,
and then halos of bad
deeds and good deeds.
We got four, how many he promised us?
Seven.
He promised us seven.
Why Nagarjuna wants to go
this way, think about it.
Number five, you okay?
[student responding indistinctly]
Yeah, non-communicating is three and four,
and communicating is one and two.
Okay, cool.
We didn't get to the mental ones yet.
,LONGS SPYOD LAS BYUNG BSOD NAMS DANG,
Oh, GZHAN DAG KYANG NI
DE BZHIN 'DOD means...
GZHAN DAG KYANG NI DE BZHIN 'DOD means
apply that to all the others,
apply that to all the others.
And he means by that, good or bad.
Okay? Good or bad.
When I'm dividing things into good or bad,
you know, keep doing that
with the rest of them.
LONGS SPYOD LAS BYUNG BSOD NAMS DANG
This is interesting.
Material good deeds
relating to the Dharma.
Making a donation to save
books with the Gold Club
or making a donation to build
a stupa for Medicine Buddha.
And that has a special name in Abhidharma,
@.
It's very interesting.
Like I spent 30 years fixing
the temple in New Jersey,
the Mongolian monastery.
I did, I rebuilt many of the
houses and stuff like that.
And I'm still getting interest on those,
as long as some monk is
sitting in that house,
I'm getting interest, karmic interest.
That's called @.
So what is number five?
It's, Nagarjuna thinks it's important
to isolate this special karma you get
from physical donations or
contributions to the Dharma,
which will outlive you
or which will outlive
your current participation
after you quit the Gold Club.
If the Gold Club saved a lot of books,
then every time Geshe-la
uses that book in a class,
you're still getting karmic interest.
It's cool.
Now, for some reason, Nagarjuna thinks
it's important to separate that one out.
So that could be a whole conversation
in a study group or something.
All right, which means that the
Medicine Buddha stupa project
and saving the books project
are interesting projects
because you keep getting
interest out of them,
even if you quit the group, you
still get the interest of it.
All right, cool.
I'm still getting interest from all the...
like I built a water system in Sera May.
So every time some monk takes a drink,
I'm like getting more karma.
All right, BSOD NAMS MA YIN TSUL DE BZHIN.
The same applies to the opposite,
and Choney Lama says building a facility
for killing cows would be an example.
If you build it and then
they keep killing cows there,
you keep getting karmic interest.
That's six, we've done six.
What's number seven going to be?
SEMS PA
The pre-intent, the pre-intent.
Like what was your intention
before you did those six?
What were you hoping
would be accomplished?
Good or bad.
But he puts them
together, so that's seven.
So we don't get an equal number
because he puts some together.
Okay, LAS SU MNGON PAR 'DOD PA YIN.
Somebody super accepts that,
@
Who?
The Buddha.
Those are the divisions
to what he first described
as only two, SEMS PA and BSAM PA.
Chetana and chetayitva.
Now, you've got seven.
Any difficult verse yet?
I think he's going to kick us in the butt,
I think something's coming.
I'm just guessing.
There's a picture, try to
find a picture of these seven.
Good luck.
I was thinking, you know, good
and bad karma or something?
I don't know.
Anyway, let's skip on.
GAL TE SMIN PA'I DUS BAR DU
Now, finally, ha-ha, why did he set us up
with this calm, understandable,
discussion of karma?
Because this was coming.
,GAL TE SMIN PA'I DUS BAR DU,
,GNAS NA LAS DE RTAG PAR 'GYUR,
,GAL TE 'GAGS NA 'GAGS GYUR PA,
,JI LTAR 'BRAS BU SKYE PAR 'GYUR,
Now he's like, here's Nagarjuna like,
"Wow, so we did all these kinds of karma,
well what happens after that?"
What do you think happens after that?
Where does the karma stay until it ripens?
And now, he was setting us
up for three verses, right?
Five verses.
He was setting us up.
And now he asks this innocent question,
"Oh, where does the karma
stay until it ripens?"
And then he's like, two possibilities:
if it stays somewhere
inert until it comes out,
well then it's RTAG PA,
it's unchanging, during that period.
It has to replicate itself as the same,
it has to clone itself from
year to year until it ripens.
So that's unchanging, that's RTAG PA,
and that's impossible
for a functional thing.
No functional entity in the
universe can not change,
even for one minute, forget
12 lifetimes or something.
Not possible.
So can we, here's Nagarjuna,
"Can we cancel the first possibility
that it sits there in
your brain not changing?"
Yeah, it has to change.
If it's a functional thing it changes.
Why?
Because it's pushed by a cause
and that energy starts to slow
down as it goes through time.
Now, oh Geshe-la, you're
saying the longer a karma
stays in your mind the
less strong it gets?
[students laughing]
Okay, well here's the other choice.
GAL TE 'GAGS NA 'GAGS GYUR PA'I
JI LTAR 'BRAS BU SKYE PAR 'GYUR,
If you say it's not
unchanging, then it stops,
and we don't have to experience
the result of the karma, yay!
Does it replicate or does it stop?
It can't replicate because
then it would stay the same
and it's a functioning thing,
and it can't stop or else
all the laws of karma would be broken.
If it stops all the laws
of karma would be broken.
You could do whatever you want
and hope that the karma
stops before it opens.
Okay?
Did you ever think about it? No.
Okay, somebody tell me why
the next picture is relevant.
Did you ever apply for
a job in New York or LA?
I'm asking my [laughs],
you spent hours in waiting rooms, right?
Were you the same person who
went into the waiting room?
I mean, to me your karma is like,
goes in the writing room and
then finally some one says
okay I am interviewing you.
You know what they always say?
They say, "Oh it's five o'clock,
can you come back tomorrow?"
You say, "I've been here
since three o'clock."
They say yeah but...
That's called applying for a
job in New York or LA, right?
Okay, you know.
All right, next verse.
And by the way, the final two verses
of what I chose for this class,
and we'll continue in the next class,
because this is a long chapter.
Two lower schools come and
try to explain the question.
So I assume some bigger
school's going to come later,
I don't know, I didn't read ahead.
But here's the answer of the MDO SDE PA,
the Sutra school, second school,
and the, what do you call that?
KHA CHE, KHA CHE
which means Kashmiris,
the guys from Kashmir.
Which means an Abhidharma school
that used to hang out in northern India.
Later, that area became Muslim,
and now the Tibetan word
for Muslim is Kashmiri.
KHA CHEs, same word.
Like @, right?
Okay, here we go.
,MYU GU LA SOGS RGYUN GANG NI,
,SA BON LAS NI MNGON PAR 'BYUNG,
,DE LAS 'BRAS BU SA BON NI,
,MED NA DE YANG 'BYUNG MI 'GYUR,
First you have the seed.
By the way, who's this? Lower Buddhists.
Well, first you have,
they're answering Nagarjuna,
"First you have the seed."
MYU GU LA SOGS RGYUN GANG YIN
And then it opens and there's a flow.
Sorry, before it opens.
First you have the seed,
and then something comes
out which is a flow.
Here's the seed, the flow
comes and breaks out,
and then it ripens, so no problem.
It's not that the seed
is repeating itself,
which would be unchanging,
which is impossible.
The seed produces something right away,
it's called the flow of the karma.
Here's the seed, karma opens, comes out.
Wait, boop, [vocalizing].
Okay, and that's the
ripening of the karma.
So no problem.
- Does the seed ripen
into the karma right away?
- No, it flows.
- And then what happens?
- At the end of the flow
it opens into the result.
Got it?
Therefore, no problem.
It's still changing because it's flowing,
but the karmic result hasn't opened yet.
Got it? No problem.
Seed, flow, result.
Got it?
That's the lower Buddhist school.
DE LAS 'BRAS BU SA BON NI
And then comes the result.
MED NA DE YANG 'BYUNG MI 'GYUR
The result could not have
happened without the seed first,
therefore the result is
connected to the seed.
If the seed had never happened,
the result, at the end of the flow,
never would've come out.
Therefore the seed is causing the result,
but via a flow.
So they get out of the question
that the seed didn't cause the result.
The seed came before the
result, it did cause the result,
it just took awhile and it was flowing.
That's their thing.
GANG PHYIR SA BON LAS RGYUN DANG
How does that work again?
There's a SA BON, there's a seed,
then there's a flow, RGYUN,
and then RGYUN LAS 'BRAS BU.
Then the flow turns into the result.
And because the seed
must predate the result,
we avoid your two extremes.
We avoid your two extremes
which is another version of
the two husbands extremes,
which is a more simple version
of the two husbands extremes,
which means does the seed ever stop,
or does the seed go on unchanging?
Both of those are extremes.
Why?
If the seed shut down
before the result came out
there'd never be a result.
If the seed kept going on the same way
until the result came out,
that would be unchanging,
and that's not possible
for a functional thing.
So just, it's just the flow,
man, stay with the flow.
[laughs] Okay?
Who is that lower school, all right?
By the way, then the Nagarjuna's like,
Nagarjuna, you know,
everybody's looking at
these lower Buddhist
guys like this, you know?
Huh?
And they say, "Oh let's explain,
let us explain further."
Which usually means digging
a deeper hole for themselves.
You know, Nagarjuna's like what?
And they're like the next two verses is,
the next two verses is their
clarification of their position.
By the way, if you don't have
Choney Lama you don't know that.
It sounds like Nagarjuna.
So anyway, @'GYUR.
Okay, the flow of the
mind comes from the mind.
DE LAS 'BRAS BU
And then that turns into the result.
The mind begets a mental flow,
and then the mental flow
turns into the result.
Three steps.
DE LAS 'BRAS BU.
BUS, he uses instrumental, B-U-S.
BUS, which means therefore,
the other guy is drawing a conclusion.
Because there's a mind and
because then the flow of the mind
and then the result comes, but therefore
@SEMS.
@SEMS means,
it's an idiomatic expression which means
forget it without the mind,
you got to have the mind,
@SEMS means forget it if there's no mind.
- There has to be a mind.
- Why?
- I just told you: mind, flow, result.
Don't tell me you can't have a mind
at the beginning of that.
Without that, nothing.
@SEMS means
you can't dump the mind, you
got to have the mind there.
@ means, you know,
what the heck without the mind.
@SEMS... MED NA
If the mind wasn't there, 'BYUNG MI 'GYUR,
the whole process would never happen.
It has to start with
mind, then mind flows.
If you say the flow of the
mind is not part of the process
then how could you have a karma
if you didn't have any thinking.
He's like,
what do you call it [indistinct]?
[student responding indistinctly]
Logical-
You're switching terms.
- Anyway, it has to start with the mind.
- Why?
- Karma starts with the mind.
- Are you telling me there's no mind?
- No, no, no, there's mind.
- Why?
- Mind is the base of karma.
- Okay, so it's flowing, what
do you have a problem with that?
[laughs] That's all he's saying.
You never could've had a karmic
result without a mind anyway,
so don't tell me my theory
is wrong that there's a flow
because the flow happens
to be the flow of the mind,
which you agree has to be
there at the beginning.
Got it?
Okay.
%GANG PHYIR SA BON LAS RGYUN DANG NI
RGYUN LAS 'BRAS BU 'BYUNG 'GYUR ZHING
I just told you the
flow comes from the mind
and then the mind keeps flowing,
and then at the end of the flow
you get a 'BRAS BU, you get a result.
LAS NI 'BRAS BU'I SNGON 'GRO BA
DE PHYIR CHAD MIN RTAG MA YIN
And because the planting
of the karma in the mind
has to predate the result,
I avoid your problems,
the two problems that you suggested.
What were the two problems we suggested?
Number one that the karmic seed
would keep replicating
itself, unchangedly,
or that it would just,
what do you call that?
Truncate.
Got it?
That's a perfect word
actually, write that down.
All right, we finished the
first half of that chapter.
We will continue with
deep dive class number 13
in the next lesson.
Let's summarize.
Nagarjuna set us up with
some understandable stuff
at the beginning, right?
What is karma? Thinking
and then the actions motivated
by thinking and speech.
And then he got into
seven different kinds,
which included the halo stuff
and emphasized,
had a noticeable bias
towards physical Dharma actions,
supporting physical,
like the input project.
And then he went on to
discuss whether or not what?
How does the seed stay in mind?
If it doesn't change there's a problem,
if it does stop there's a problem.
And then we had an attempted
explanation by some guys
who keep talking about
some kind of flow thing
that connects the result
to the original seed
without the seed changing or stopping.
Cool?
All right, see you next class.